Samuel V. Hulse

Postdoctral Associate Theoretical Evolutionary Biologist

Address: Phone: (443) 527-5710) Email: shulse@umd.edu 1350 Shepherd St NW

Washington, DC 20011 GitHub: svhulse

Professional Interests

For my doctoral work, I focused on expanding the domain of the sensory drive model beyond peripheral sensory processing, to explain the evolution of complex visual displays. In the Bruns Lab, I am working to develop theoretical models for how evolutionary feedbacks influence disease resistance in plant models. My understanding of the field has been greatly informed by my passion for mathematics, and I am captivated by how evolutionary theory can be made more rigorous through interdisciplinary approaches.

Professional Experience

Postdoctoral Associate 2021 - Curr.

University of Maryland College Park, Baltimore, MD

Supervisor: Dr. Emily Bruns

Education

2021 Ph.D., Biological Sciences

University of Maryland Baltimore County, Baltimore, MD

Dissertation: The Evolution of Visual Patterning in North American Freshwater Fishes

Supervisor: Dr. Tamra Mendelson

2021 M.S., Applied Mathematics

University of Maryland Baltimore County, Baltimore, MD

B.S., Environmental Science 2012

Juniata College, Huntingdon, PA

Peer-Reviewed Publications

2023 Hulse, S.V., Antonovics, J., Hood, M.E., and Bruns, E.L. Host-pathogen coevolution promotes the evolution of general, broad-spectrum resistance and reduces foreign pathogen

spillover risk. In Review.

2023

Hulse, S.V., Antonovics, J., Hood, M.E., and Bruns, E.L. Specific resistance prevents the evolution of general resistance and facilitates disease emergence. Journal of Evolutionary

Riology '	26. 71	50 760

- Hulse, S.V., Renoult, J.P., and Mendelson, T.C. Using deep neural networks to model similarity between visual patterns: Application to fish sexual signals. *Ecological Informatics* 67: 101486.
- Hulse, S.V., Renoult, J.P., and Mendelson, T.C. Sexual signaling pattern correlates with habitat pattern in visually ornamented fishes. *Nature Communications* 11: 2561.

Conferences and Presentations

Invited Talks

- Hulse, S.V. The evolution and maintenance of host genetic diversity for pathogen resistance. Mathematical Biology Seminar, University of Maryland College Park.
- Hulse, S.V. Applications of Deep Learning to Fish Behavioral Patterns. Machine Learners Group Seminar, Scripps Institution of Oceanography.
- 2019 **Hulse, S.V.** Understanding the signals animals send each other. High School Assembly Presentation, The Park School of Baltimore.

Contributed Talks

- 2023 **Hulse, S.V.** The role of coevolution in mantaining host resistance structures. Evolution, Albuquerque, NM.
- 2023 **Hulse, S.V.** Does host-pathogen coevolution increase the risk of foreign pathogen invasion? Ecology and Evolution of Infectious Diseases, State College, PA.
- 2021 **Hulse, S.V.** Visual statistsics of habitat predict spatial aspect of visual signals. University of Maryland Behavior, Ecology, Evolution, and Systematics Department Retreat, Thurmont, MD.
- Mendelson, T.C., **Hulse, S.V.,** Renoult, J.P. Complex nuptial patterns of fish species mimic the spatial statistics of their habitat. Annual meeting of the Animal Behavior Society, Chicago, IL.
- 2018 Hulse, S.V. The Efficient Coding Hypothesis and Signal Design. UMBC Biological Sciences Departmental Seminar, Baltimore, MD.
- 2018 **Hulse**, **S.V.**, and Mendelson, T.C. The efficient coding hypothesis and signal design. Annual meeting of the Society for Integrative and Comparative Biology, San Francisco, CA.
- 2017 **Hulse, S.V.,** and Mendelson, T.C. The efficient coding hypothesis and signal design. Spotlight Talk, Evolution, Portland, OR.

	Posters
2022	Hulse, S.V. , and Bruns. E.L. Disease Resistance at the Whole Organism Level, The Joint Evolution of General and Specific Resistance. Ecology and Evolution of Infectious Diseases, Atlanta GA.
2020	Hulse, S.V., Mendelson, T.C., and Renoult, J.P. The spatial statistics of sexual signals in fishes correspond to their habitat: extending sensory drive to signal design. NSF workshop: Biology through Information Communication Coding Theory, Alexandria, VA.
2018	Hulse, S.V., Renoult, J.P., and Mendelson, T.C. The Efficient Coding Hypothesis and the Evolution of Signal Design. Evolution, Montpellier, France.
2017	Hulse, S.V., and Mendelson, T.C. The efficient coding hypothesis and signal design. Annual meeting of the Society for Integrative and Comparative Biology, New Orleans, LA.
	Grants, Awards, and Fellowships
	Fellowships
2019	Millhauser Fellowship, The Park School of Baltimore (\$250)
2018	Chateaubriand Fellowship, The Embassy of France in the United States (\$4200)
	Travel Awards
2020	NSF BIOtIC Workshop Student Support (Housing Support)
2018	SICB Charlotte Magnum Student Support (Housing Support)
2018	SICB Charlotte Magnum Student Support (Housing Support)
2018	Wilson Ornithological Society Travel Award (\$285)
	Other Awards
2018	AAAS/Science Program for Excellence in Science (Full AAAS Membership benefits)
	Training
2022	University of Maryland Mentoring Workshops for Postdoctoral Fellows, College Park, MD. MIT Brains, Minds Machines Virtual Summer Course, Woods Hole, MA.
	Teaching Experience
2015-2021	Teaching Assistant, Comparative Vertebrate Physiology Lab
2016-2020	Teaching Assistant, Anatomy and Physiology II Lab
2018	Guest Lecturer, Sexual Selection

2017, 2018 Guest Lecturer, Animal Behavior

Mentoring

Undergraduate Mentoring, University of Maryland College Park

2023 Molly Gans, Amherst University

2022 Daniel Fu, University of Maryland College Park

Academic Service

Manuscript Peer Reviewed

2023 Biology Letters (Joint review with Dr. Emily Bruns)

2022 Evolutionary Ecology2020 Behavioral Ecology

Misc. Service

2023 - Curr. Organiser: Mathmatical Biology Journal Club

2023 SSE W. D. Hamilton Award Judge

2023 Maryland Day 2023 Outreach Volunteer

2016-2020 UMBC Department of Biological Science FUN Committee

2016-2017 UMBC Graduate Student Association Senator